<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>http://munindranath.github.io/pelican/</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds%5Csideproject.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2014-01-30T17:50:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>2 cents</title><link href="/2-cents.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-30T17:50:00+01:00</updated><author><name>sideproject</name></author><id>tag:,2014-01-30:2-cents.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My 2 cents to me and Confucius overdose&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Confucius said, “To merely know is nothing compared to being interested
to know, being interested to know is nothing compared to deriving joy
from learning it”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different things pop-up when I am (trying) to study or read. And it’s
been this way since ever. But this time I want to know why it happens,
why it rarely happens when I am watching a movie or playing tennis. Why,
when I watch interesting movie or any series, I can’t stop it in the
middle and watch the remaining later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going by Confucius again, “He that would perfect his work must first
sharpen his tools.”, I thought I need to work on my tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do I lack concentration in reading or study?\
 With some introspection and little reading, this is what I found. It
seems like I don’t engage with the material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How am I able to engage with movies or playing tennis?\
 I think they are couple of reasons:\
 1. Interest: Not all movies are engaging; not all tennis games at
engaging but mostly they are. What’s the reason?\
 2. Relation: I wouldn’t mind watch 3 hours Bollywood movie or 4 hours
Tennis matches or may be whole day of Cricket but I don’t think I could
ever watch “curling”. Reason for that, I don’t have appreciation for
that game. Why? Because I don’t know what’s so special about it. I don’t
know the history of it. I can’t relate myself with it.\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://sideproject.me/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/curling.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="curling" src="http://sideproject.me/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/curling-300x241.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;\
 3. Practice to Play/Learn: This goes back to first 2 points, when I am
not interested and it doesn’t relate to me; I really don’t care to spend
time practice or learn. Like anything, studying and reading are
activities with different levels and one can get better if the basics
are sound and practicing it would make foundation solid. If the basics
are not strong and if we are working with advanced level then
frustration is natural. This leads to the next point.\
 4. Suck at it: Now that I know I suck at it, I generally give up. The
frustration and disgust creeps in and stays. Whenever I think about
reading again, the feeling associated with it comes back on the surface
and without even starting, I just give up mentally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to overcome this?\
 This is what I have been trying:\
 1. Starting small\
 a. Reading material: Trying to find easy to understand and small (under
150 pages) reading material. Finishing these materials give me
confidence.\
 b. Time: Give myself little goals like to read 5 pages every day. Then
read 10 pages. Then read 10 pages in 20 mins etc. This has helped a lot.
Breaking the book 10 – 20 pages a day is really helpful. And I am
excited to come back to the book again to read what might happen again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. Actively Engaging: I am doing some investigation in advance to start
of my reading journey. This is really helping in painting the mental
canvas when I read. I am able to put things in context, relate to them
and understand better. This process is still under process and I really
hope that I continue this. How am I doing this:\
 a. Knowing the Author: This is really cool. The other day, I was just
reading about Charles Dickens. His life stories, struggles, motivations,
and his styles. “The Great Expectation” made more sense to me. I can see
Dickens telling story, I can see his story in the Novel. It’s
unbelievable how my perspective changed, just by knowing more about the
author.\
 b. Knowing the plot/context of the reading material: Try to find
resources which can give little idea what the book is about, what is
setting, important characters, etc. It gets me ready for the book, I
know what to expect.\
 c. Relate more: I am excited to know about the details. I ask how, why,
where, things are happening. I feel by this I kind of make connection
with the text. Asking questions definitely makes reading active and
engaging.\
 d. Taking notes: This is still under process, I haven’t been good a
taking notes. One of my biggest note-taking flaws is that I write down
all the important looking text from the book I am reading. And this what
happens:\
 i. I am putting more effort in making notes than reading\
 ii. My notes are exact copy of the book ( basically waste of time)\
 iii. Loose the joy of reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the things I intend to do:\
 i. Write down words and sentences and not worry about making the
perfect notes\
 ii. Write my question and try to find answers\
 iii. Explain in my own words&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;e. Ponder what I read; what my takeaways from the book are. Can I
explain to someone what I read?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like Confucius said, “He, who learns but does not think, is lost. He who
thinks but does not learn is in great danger.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Articles:\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.myrkothum.com/the-7-habits-of-highly-effective-people-1-private-victory/\
 http://calnewport.com/\
 http://www.scotthyoung.com/blog/&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>how to read</title><link href="/how-to-read.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-17T22:58:00+01:00</updated><author><name>sideproject</name></author><id>tag:,2014-01-17:how-to-read.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Found some some interesting blogs related to how to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://classicalbookworm.wordpress.com/2006/08/28/two-books-forward-three-books-back/\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://classicalbookworm.wordpress.com/2006/10/03/the-art-of-note-taking/\
 http://www.bbc.co.uk/worldservice/programmes/the_word.shtml\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://classicalbookworm.wordpress.com/2005/10/04/the-well-educated-mind/\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://darjeelingclassic.wordpress.com/well-educated-mind-by-susan-wise-bauer/\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/07/books/the-last-word-the-great-books-workout.html?pagewanted=all&amp;amp;src=pm\
 http://www.classicalquest.com/2012/04/book-that-changed-my-life.html\
 http://www.21learn.org/archive/review-the-educated-mind/\
 http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_WCfaGarc4U&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Reading</title><link href="/reading.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-08T22:55:00+01:00</updated><author><name>sideproject</name></author><id>tag:,2014-01-08:reading.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This I would like to read during GMAT prep process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. "The Well-Educated Mind" - Susan Wise Bauer\
 2. "How to Read a Book" - Mortimer J. Adler, Charles Van Doren\
 3. "How to Develop Perfect Memory" - Dominic O'Brien\
 4. "Breakthrough Rapid Reading" - Peter Kump&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interesting Blog posts:\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.ryanholiday.net/read-to-lead-how-to-digest-books-above-your-level/\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.farnamstreetblog.com/2011/01/how-do-excellent-performers-differ-from-the-average/\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.farnamstreetblog.com/2013/05/the-buffett-formula-how-to-get-smarter/\
 http://www.farnamstreetblog.com/2013/09/finding-time-to-read/&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>10 weeks GMAT study plan</title><link href="/10-weeks-gmat-study-plan.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-07T15:43:00+01:00</updated><author><name>sideproject</name></author><id>tag:,2014-01-07:10-weeks-gmat-study-plan.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Week 1 – GMAT Research and Study Plan Details&lt;/strong&gt;\
 Learn square till 25, root till 10, prime number till 200, tables till
20, quick multiplication tricks\
 Vocab, Idioms,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read 6 articles from NYTimes, paraphrase in the blog&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weeks Two to Four – Math Focus&lt;/strong&gt;\
 Topic Revision 15mins/topic\
 FlashCards&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read 6 articles from NYTimes, paraphrase in the blog&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weeks Fifth to Seventh – Verbal Focus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read 6 articles from NYTimes, paraphrase in the blog&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weeks Eight to Tenth – Practice Tests and Review of Errors&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read 6 articles from NYTimes, paraphrase in the blog&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would be expanding this as I get more aware of things.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>gmat structure and scoring explained</title><link href="/gmat-structure-and-scoring-explained.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-07T14:47:00+01:00</updated><author><name>sideproject</name></author><id>tag:,2014-01-07:gmat-structure-and-scoring-explained.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Revised GMAT June 2012 — Exam Structure\
 (Total testing time: 3 hrs., 30 min.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SECTION 1: AWA—Analysis of an Argument (30 minutes, 1 essay)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SECTION 2: Integrated Reasoning (30 minutes, 12 questions)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Timed break (optional)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SECTION 3: Quantitative Section (75 minutes, 37 questions)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Problem Solving (23-24 questions)\
 Data Sufficiency (13-14 questions)\
 Timed break (optional)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SECTION 4: Verbal Section (75 minutes, 41 questions)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sentence Correction (14-15 questions)\
 Critical Reasoning (14-15 questions)\
 Reading Comprehension (4 passages, 12-14 questions)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AWA—Analysis of an Argument (30 minutes, 1 essay topic)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this exam section you'll compose an essay in which you critique a
one-paragraph argument in terms of both its logical cogency and the
strength of the evidence used to support it. The testing system will
select your Argument-Analysis prompt randomly from a large pool; you
won't be able to choose among prompts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To record your response you must use the word processor built into the
testing system. Handwritten responses are not allowed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Integrated-Reasoning Section&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The revised GMAT exam introduces a new 30-minute section called
Integrated Reasoning. This new section is designed to gauge your ability
to interpret, analyze and evaluate textual and graphical information
presented in realistic, business-related formats. Test takers are
awarded a separate score for this new section, on a 0-8 scale — as
distinguished from the 0-60 scale used for the Quantitative and Verbal
sections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Quantitative Section (75 minutes, 37 questions)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This multiple-choice section is designed to measure your basic math,
algebra and geometry skills, your understanding of basic quantitative
concepts, and your ability to reason quantitatively, solve quantitative
problems and interpret graphical data. Each Quantitative question will
conform to one of two different formats: either Problem Solving or Data
Sufficiency (questions in the two formats are intermingled):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Problem Solving (23-24 questions): Questions in this format require you
to work to a solution, which will appear among the five answer choices.\
 Data Sufficiency (13-14 questions): Each question in this format
consists of a question followed by two statements (labeled 1 and 2).
Your task is to determine whether the information provided in the two
statements suffices to answer the question. The five answer choices are
the same for each and every Data-Sufficiency question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;he GMAT Quantitative Section — Skills Tested and Math Topics Covered&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GMAT CAT includes one Quantitative section. Here are the key
features of this exam section:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time limit: 75 minutes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exam section number: Section 3 (the third of four exam sections)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Number of questions: 37 available questions (approximately 2 minutes per
question, on average)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basic format: All questions are multiple choice (five choices)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skills tested:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your basic math and algebra skills\
 Your understanding of basic quantitative concepts\
 Your ability to reason quantitatively, solve quantitative problems and
interpret data presented graphically\
 Knowledge Levels and Math Topics Covered&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GMAT Quantitative section covers quantitative concepts typically
covered in basic high-school math coursework. It does not cover
trigonometry, calculus or other advanced math topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A GMAT Quantitative question might involve any of the math topics listed
below. The number of questions from each broad category (in bold face)
can vary slightly from the ranges indicated here because some questions
will fit into more than one category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Arithmetic, number theory, statistics (14-15 questions)\
 arithmetical operations\
 the number line and ordering\
 integers, factors and multiples\
 decimals, percentages, and ratios\
 exponents and square roots\
 mean, median, mode, range, standard deviation\
 basic probability\
 number patterns (series, permutations, factorials)\
 Interpretation of graphical data (3-5 questions)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tabular data (tables)\
 line charts, bar charts and scatter charts\
 pie graphs\
 Algebra (11-12 questions)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;operations on variables\
 factorable binomials and polynomials\
 algebraic equations\
 algebraic functions\
 algebraic inequalities\
 Geometry (6-8 questions)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;lines and angles\
 triangles, quadrilaterals and other polygons\
 properties and characteristics of circles\
 3-dimensional solids\
 coordinate geometry&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Verbal Section (75 minutes, 41 questions)\
 This multiple-choice section includes the following three different
question types, which are intermingled rather than grouped separately.
Every Verbal question comes with five answer choices.\
 Sentence Correction (14-15 questions): These questions are designed to
gauge you command of the English language and the conventions of
standard written English, including grammar, syntax (sentence structure)
and diction — but not punctuation. For each question your task is to
determine which among five versions of a sentence is the best example of
proper grammar and effective expression.\
 Critical Reasoning (14-15 questions): These questions are designed to
gauge your ability to understand, critique, and draw reasonable
conclusions from arguments. Each argument is presented in a brief (one-
or two-paragraph) passage of text.\
 Reading Comprehension (12-14 questions): These questions are designed
to measure your ability to read carefully and accurately, to determine
the relationships among the various parts of a reading passage, and to
draw reasonable inferences from the information in the passage. The
questions are presented in sets of 3-4, each set based on the same 150
to 350-word passage of text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Two Timed Breaks&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GMAT testing system provides two timed breaks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first break comes after Section 2 (Integrated Reasoning) — i.e.,
after 60 minutes of actual exam time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second break comes after Section 3 (the Quantitative section) —
i.e., after another 75 minutes of actual exam time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both breaks are optional; you may terminate either break at any time and
proceed to the next test section.\
 Immediately after each timed break the next test section will
automatically begin. So if you take too long a break, the additional
time will be deducted from the next test section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Score Report&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An official GMAT score report consists of five parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. Verbal Scaled Score (on a scale from 0 to 60)\
 2. Quantitative Scaled Score (on a scale from 0 to 60)\
 3. Total Scaled Score (on a scale from 200 to 800)\
 4. Analytical Writing Assessment (AWA) Score (on a scale from 0 to 6)\
 5. Integrated Reasoning Score (on a scale from 1 to 8)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The total score is a scaled combination of the verbal and quantitative
scaled scores, and thus reflects a student’s overall performance on the
multiple-choice sections of the test. The AWA and the Integrated
Reasoning sections are scored independently; scores for these sections
do not affect the 200-800 scaled score.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Verbal and Quantitative Sections&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To compute the scaled score for the Verbal and Quantitative sections,
GMAT uses an algorithm that takes the following factors into account:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. number of questions answered within the time permitted\
 2. number of questions answered correctly\
 3. statistical characteristics (including level of difficulty) of the
questions answered&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of each section, the GMAT presents a question in the
middle range of difficulty. If the question is answered correctly, the
next question will be harder and the test-taker's score will adjust
upwards. If the question is answered incorrectly, the next question will
be easier, and the test-taker’s score will adjust downwards. (The test
taker does not see this adjustment because the score is not revealed
until the entire test has been completed.) Thus, the algorithm is
constantly recalculating the scaled score as the student progresses
through the section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a test-taker answers more questions, the algorithm receives more
information about his or her skills and is able to calculate an accurate
score with greater and greater precision. Consequently, the questions at
the beginning of the section are weighted much more heavily than
questions near the end of the section. For example, by the time Question
36 appears, the computer has had 35 questions from which to derive the
proper score range. So even if Question 36 were answered correctly, the
increase in score would be minimal compared to the increase in score if
Question 2 had been answered correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References:\
 http://www.testmasters.net/gmatabout/scoring-scale\
 http://www.west.net/\~stewart/gmat/introduction.htm&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>routine</title><link href="/routine.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-03T19:33:00+01:00</updated><author><name>sideproject</name></author><id>tag:,2014-01-03:routine.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Plan for next few months, as I would be giving GMAT. The current plan
might be little ambitious, but I would like to put around 3hrs on
weekdays and 6hrs on the weekend for GMAT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My routine:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WeekDays\
 4:00am Getup\
 MEDITATION\
 4:30 - 7:00am GMAT study\
 8:00-5:00pm work\
 6:00-7:30pm dinner\
 7:30-9:00pm GMAT/REVISION\
 Plan for next day\
 9:30pm Bed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WeekEnds\
 4:00am Getup\
 MEDITATION\
 4:30 - 7:30am GMAT study\
 8:30 - 11:00pm study\
 3:00 - 5:00pm study\
 8:00 - 9:00pm revision\
 Plan for next day\
 9:30pm Bed&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>thursday</title><link href="/thursday.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-02T20:24:00+01:00</updated><author><name>sideproject</name></author><id>tag:,2014-01-02:thursday.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Finally able to make some website structure. I wanted to do this for a
long time. I am happy about this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plan for 2014:\
 This is year already packed with work/personal commitments. Couple of
things I would like to achieve in 2014 would be:\
 1. Run half marathon. Registered for a race on March 8th.\
 2. Give GMAT in April.\
 3. Document my daily progress in log section.\
 4. Not to overwhelm with plenty of things to do.\
 5. Eat very clean, gluten-free/vegan.\
 6. Meditate 15mins everyday.\
 7. Minimize useless internet browsing.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Home</title><link href="/home.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-01-09T22:20:00+01:00</updated><author><name>sideproject</name></author><id>tag:,2013-01-09:home.html</id><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title>No title [68]</title><link href="/68.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-01-09T22:18:00+01:00</updated><author><name>sideproject</name></author><id>tag:,2013-01-09:68.html</id><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title>No title [69]</title><link href="/69.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-01-09T22:18:00+01:00</updated><author><name>sideproject</name></author><id>tag:,2013-01-09:69.html</id><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title>No title [70]</title><link href="/70.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-01-09T22:18:00+01:00</updated><author><name>sideproject</name></author><id>tag:,2013-01-09:70.html</id><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>